What does Africa mean to me...
Like Estonia,
a lovely part of the world.
Well, Africa to me means Ghana.
And kind of sweet...
I don't know how to answer it.
Ghana - a former British Gold Coast,
is located in West Africa.
A country of which surface area
is equal to UK
could be a paradise on earth.
On the shores of the Atlantic Ocean
next to the Gulf of Guinea run sunny
sand beaches, grow coconut trees
and the water is always warm.
Ghana's bowels of the earth hide
so much gold, that it is being sold
in tens of tons every year
to the rest of the world.
Ancient Shea trees grow in the
savannas of Northern Ghana
bearing valuable fruit,
and the people living there are
rather peaceful and hospitable.
Although the country is developing
and getting richer,
people living in the villages are
poor and make do with very little.
You cannot get cheese there. - Why?
- They don't have any cheese there.
I should have warned you,
so that you had taken your last
cheese sandwich with you.
When you are there for a long time
you will start craving for cheese.
The best thing is parmesan.
OUR WORLD
ESTONIAN VILLAGE IN GHANA
Diana Tamm is a reformer. She studied
to be an art teacher and art critic,
but ended up in Kongo village
in Ghana as a volunteer.
Kongo village is located in the north
700 km from the capital city Accra.
Being a volunteer became her job.
Now Diana helps to develop business
in Africa through NGO Mondo
in order to help better the quality
of life for the local women.
Now I am visiting for the 5th time.
All my next visits to the Kongo
village will be dealing
with basket weavers and production
and development of Shea butter.
Hi, hi! How are you?
The joy of reunion is great.
Village women waited for Diana's
arrival for months.
Estonians who accompany her
are also welcomed as old friends.
Welcome! Thank you!
Welcome! You say - Nambaa!
Kongo Village in North Ghana next to
the border of Burkina Faso
is exactly one of those places
where Ghana's economic development
reaches very slowly.
In the village of many
thousand people
women who have lost their husband
struggle the most
because the man is responsible for
providing for his family.
Diana's arrival is long awaited
because with her help tens of women
in Kongo village are hopeful to start
their own business.
With the help of Estonians
a local Shea butter factory will
hopefully be started.
Shea butter is justifiably called
African women's gold,
because both cosmetics
and food production industries
have discovered this raw material and
there would be enough market for it.
Diana brings with her two business
women from Estonia
who want to buy the Shea butter -
African women's gold.
So you remember last time I was
telling you that there are
some ladies who are interested in
your Shea butter,
but they wanted to come here but the
plains were not flying...
So we were waiting and waiting but
they could not come.
I think we are very grateful
that they have come.
And you have a chance to talk to
each other and meet each other
and discuss the business you could
do together. So I will introduce.
This is Kati ... And she will have a
local name afterwards, right?
And this is Kai.
A little Shea butter factory
is in a way
like an Estonian Embassy
in the Kongo village.
Women are proud to wave the Estonian
flag and both the gate and
the workshop's wall are painted
blue, black and white.
Today the elaborate reception
has been arranged
for the guests who
have arrived from the mother country.
Introducing Kai Lepik and
Kati Mäekalda is important
because trust in Ghana's society
is built through previous
acquaintances and friendship.
Every guest receives a new name that
bears a certain local meaning
referring to their personal identity
or to some god.
Arrival of the guests and reception
with the dance gives both parties
hope that the business will
be fruitful.
Estonians don't want to
be worse dancers than Ghana women
and make their feet skip fast.
The trust is built that way.
A Shea butter factory
has been built here by Mondo.
We would want to start exporting it
to EU and America
that is why we are
here. We will try to do it.
As a surprise to us, Shea butter is
being used mainly in food production.
We knew that it was being used
more in cosmetics industry.
We will start selling the Shea butter
first to private consumers
and start searching for people and
bigger organisations
that will use it in cosmetics
industry.
Shea tree grows naturally in dry
savannas
in central zone of African
continent.
The fruit of the tree is sour-sweet
and very nutritious.
In the middle of the pulp there is a
part of the nut that is rich in oil
and today has become like gold.
The tree starts bearing fruit only in
10 - 15 years
and does that for two centuries.
Shea butter is amazing in many ways -
in cosmetics industry
Shea butter is valued for its
moisture and healing properties.
Unrefined butter is especially
valuable because producing it
is a time consuming handicraft.
Locals use Shea butter mainly
for cooking purposes -
a spoonful of Shea butter
gives the food a good nutty taste,
adding nutrients and vitamins.
We bring the nuts from office.
HOSTESS OF THE SHEA CO-OPERATIVE
We wash them. After washing
we dry it. After drying we take it
to the crushing we do the crushing,
after the crushing,
we bring it back to our kitchen.
We roast it up to one hour. Or more.
It depends how you feed to fire.
During the picking season
they are normally wet.
But now they are dry and you can
roast them for one hour.
After one hour you cool it down.
And you take it to the grand mill.
You mill it. Bring it out again.
Add water.
You do the kneading,
mix it and extract oil.
Then you take it back to the fire.
You boil for some time.
You get the oil
and leave the rest there.
Shea butter production starts in the
factory's courtyard after the fruit
has been picked
and the nuts are in bags.
Women wash the nuts,
place them to dry in the sun and pick
out the unsuitable nuts one by one.
Sorted dry nuts need to be crushed -
even that was hand craft before.
While crushing the mill room is
filled with sweet cocoa like smell,
even though the nuts themselves
taste bitter.
Crushed nuts will be roasted
in a closed drum on an open fire.
It all takes time
and adds more heat to a day
that is already 40 degree heat.
Roasted nuts will be dried again
in the sun.
Crushed and roasted nuts
will be ground fine in the mill
and will become a creamy melted
chocolate like mixture.
Brown paste will need to be mixed
little by little with water
followed by strong kneading.
Bending over the bowl work
and working with hand in the desert
heat will slowly bring the fat
from Shea nut to the surface.
The separated mass is Shea butter
that needs to be drained
with water many times.
Shea butter is washed manually
many times.
At last the Shea butter
needs to be boiled.
Work will go on the whole day and
boiling starts only in the dark.
Golden yellow boiling hot butter
is lifted to a clean container
and left to cool until the morning.
Opportunity to produce Shea butter
from beginning to an end
in the new factory is a big step
forward for Kongo village women
and more important
than we can imagine.
It is important, because it has
opened our eyes and our ability,
to come together, to help each other.
It has now brought unity
to us widows who are here.
We can now come together, work and
after we can all have some income
to bring home to our families.
Shea butter has cooled down by the
morning and the packaging begins.
Those women have passed the health
inspection earlier,
washed their hands thoroughly and are
wearing work uniform. The Shea butter
cannot be contaminated with
impurities or bacteria
after being heated up.
Standardising the packaging creates
problems at first,
because weighing
is done here for the first time.
Market here measures
things by piece or by volume.
Now the women need to start looking
at the weight and measure it,
how much is that 100 or 200 grams
that gets left over
from the 5 kg packet.
Bystander might get an impression
that the packer doesn't know the
numbers.
An order for fifty kilos of
Shea butter
to African women was given
by Estonians.
A long and tedious process
needs to be undergone
in order for the product
to be exported officially.
Unfortunately the new factory does
not have a certificate at the moment
and therefore the product travels to
Europe in small quantities
in the clients' suitcases.
By the way, the Shea butter was
almost confiscated
later at the airport
being considered an explosive.
This feeling that you get here,
you feel how spoiled we are
coming from the West.
Estonians are a small nation.
Even though, we consider
ourselves nature centred, etc.
They live here with very little and
are very happy!
Their joy and welcome was so sincere
and real when we arrived. Heartful.
They are so thankful first of all to
Mondo who came to this village.
Because Mondo chooses these areas
that are struggling.
These women have no work they have
nothing to do because
this is like desert here.
This is their only chance.
This project is their only
opportunity because they themselves
cannot find any clients.
Being packaged for Europeans,
after a long flight Shea butter can
be bought in Tallinn.
But producing Shea butter
is not the only thing
that Mondo is helping with in Ghana.
Baskets...
The baskets get squashed when we
transport them because
we press them into the bags so that
we can fit more of them in.
Every basket
gets a label of the weaver.
And when these baskets arrive
we have asked that they attach the
names of the weavers to the baskets.
And we also
take photos of the weavers.
We print them in Estonia. According
to the name label on the basket,
it gets the weaver's photo as well.
I can see how important it is to
the buyers in Estonia, they ask -
really, did that woman weave it?
And yes, that woman wove it.
Good morning, how are you?
- I am fine, How are you?
Weaving the baskets is an
income source for women in Ghana
who get paid very little for this
work, sometimes even so little
that a ride on the bus to the market
eats up all they make.
Twenty five cents for the basket is
not much.
At the same time weaving baskets to
be sold in Estonia
and getting the right price makes
them make more effort for quality.
Those were our basket weavers.
At the beginning we had a small group
of basket weavers - about 8 women.
Three of them are actually
from the main group.
They are more experienced weavers.
They used to weave
by themselves before
but now that we have a co-operative,
they weave together.
The group divides the orders
that have been placed from Estonia
and help each other
with the quality testing
making sure
that the patterns are right, etc.
Two of them call each other sisters
when in reality
their husbands are brothers.
They live close
to each other's households.
We shouldn't forget that Diana
has studied to be an art critic
and she has very cleverly combined
her knowledge,
the hand craft skills of Ghana women
and the wishes and paying ability of
Estonian women.
My work is mainly quality testing
and giving the women indications
as to which quality the Western buyer
is actually expecting.
All those baskets that they are
weaving here
will be sold mainly in Estonia but
there are also clients
from America and other places.
The other thing that we have done
is that all those patterns and models
have actually been created by
Estonian designers.
I also make sure that the patterns
turn out the way we have agreed
and the shape and size is right.
It is work you do with your hands
and they are not used to
measuring things here.
I am the one who measures things
and say when the basket is too wide
or something should be done
differently.
We have this kind of catalogue here
that we use for placing the orders
and they can keep an eye
on the orders.
There is also a photo of
what the basket model
looks like that they use
as an example for weaving.
If it is important to
the Estonian buyers
to know who has weaved their basket
then it is also important to
the women in Kongo village
who will buy their basket.
Just lately Kodukant,
the Estonian Village Movement,
ordered baskets from Kongo village
weavers for the recognition cause
for excellent Estonian volunteers.
The baskets were handed over
by president Toomas Hendrik Ilves
and naturally the women were proud
because it was their first time
to weave baskets
for such an important client.
So this is the president of Estonia.
And the ladies here were weaving
baskets for him
so he can present them
to the volunteers.
Unlike Shea butter
the baskets weigh little
and it is important to send them to
Estonia by post also.
In addition exporting baskets
doesn't need any special permission.
Thanks to regular orders
it is possible for Kongo village
women to count on that income.
In addition with help from Estonians
their little workshop has been fixed
and a secure fence
has been built around it.
We get asked a lot
why we are working in Africa
and not in Estonia like in Valga or
Põlva County or in Eastern Estonia.
But we say that there are plenty of
organisations who are located on
the outskirts of Estonia. We exist so
that Estonian people
can work in Africa through an
Estonian organisation.
I always think about this question
from a human point of view,
what is the difference between
Estonian children being hungry
or children in Ghana being hungry?
Every person in the world
should be fed.
Estonians' activity is
the only source
for economic growth for this village.
It is true that money surplus is also
provided by those
who get their pay from the government
teachers, county officials -
or illegal goldminers.
Otherwise the money is being circled
within the village
from sewer to the innkeeper,
from innkeeper to weaver,
from weaver to the stall keeper.
Market is the heart of this village.
The market day is every third day.
It has been divided in a way
that one day
one village has a market day,
on another day there is a market day
in the city
and on the third day there
is a market day in a bigger city.
The market is organised in rotation.
Every time you come to the village
it is important to ask when the next
market day will be, that is when you
can buy your tomatoes and bananas.
There are only a few stalls open
on a daily basis
selling biscuits, soap and water.
But most of the trading takes place
on a market day.
Market day is also for people coming
together and socialising.
It is the heart of village life.
A lot of women trade in small ways
in addition to their farming.
For example they buy 3 kg of soap
and then sell it piece by piece
and earn a little profit that way,
which of course is very small.
It gives them a reason to be active
and meet other women.
Good morning!
Let's look at the market.
The main trading areas are underneath
the little shelters.
They sell garden produce
that they have grown.
There are no scales here.
They sell by volume,
either putting something in the bowl
and pricing the bowl
or they build these towers and the
tower has a price.
In general you
cannot bargain much.
Things have their fixed
market prices.
Sometimes they add things to you.
I was given a bowlful of tomatoes
and then she gave me
three more tomatoes,
that was the bonus I was given.
Mpoo'ya (thank you)
This bag of tomatoes costs 25 cents.
One local currency is Ghana cedi.
Mango, how much? 50 pesawas.
It is mango season right now.
Mangos are so yummy, but I can see
that these ones are quite soft.
I take this one.
What are you buying?
- Mango. - They said they want beans.
Ahaa, you are buying for Lisa.
You are buying for them or they will
come and buy?
I am buying for them,
but the money is with them.
This lady is Madam Rose Adazebra.
She is a like a local activist here.
She is a member
of our basket weavers group
and also a treasurer of our
partner organisation KoCDA.
She takes care
of their money matters.
It is interesting that not many women
from her generation are educated.
Good morning! How are you?
- I'm fine, how are you, too?
Rose is an interesting woman in that
sense that not many women in
her generation are educated, not many
had an opportunity to attend school.
She is between 50 to 60 years old.
She decided to go and educate herself
and is one of the few women from her
generation who is literate.
Therefore she has taken on the role
to look after the money.
Rose is also very active
in the village.
She organises training for women from
her region and also looks after women
who have given birth, training them
in breast feeding and so on.
It is good to see here what is being
bought and sold in the village.
They mainly grow different grains.
It keeps quite well in this climate
and when they want to cook something
from it, they grind a needed portion.
If I understand correctly, these are
variations of some sort of corn.
This should be a Guinea corn.
I don't know how that is in Estonian.
Some sort of corn variation.
This is also corn? - Soy.
- Ah, soybeans?
And this one is millet?
- Yes.
And this one too millet?
Morning. - Morning.
- What is it?
Its for putting farm animals inside.
- Like chicken?
As I understand this is
like a chicken cage.
If you need to transport your
chicken, then you put it in there.
This man here is a shoe repairer. He
is repairing galebash right now.
Galebash is a pumpkin,
which they dry.
They grow these pumpkins especially
for making different dishes.
It is being used an
ordinary bowl then.
But it is especially popular for
drinking a local home made beer.
How are things going? Good!
Tidii. Thank you!
What he said to me tidii right now
means that you have been invited
to take part of the food. Whenever
someone is eating,
then in English you say
"you are invited".
What are you eating? What is it?
TZ? No-no, it's banku.
She was one of the women
who produce Shea butter.
TZ ( Tii Zeed ) or Tuo Zaafi
is one of the most widespread foods
in Northern Ghana.
It is a porridge made from corn flour
and potato like manioc flour that
is mostly being eaten with soup
made from green vegetables.
Basket weaver Rose invited Diana
for dinner tonight and naturally will
serve her the same national dish.
They are making us the same local
dish that is called Tii Zeed.
Actually it is
the main food here.
Some families have it for breakfast
and for dinner every day.
It turns into a very thick porridge
and is eaten with a sauce.
The sauce has already been made
in the other pot.
They say here - a good woman
is able to make a good Tii Zeed .
Afterwards the porridge will be
beaten in a way that requires skill.
They put in two kinds of millet
flour and water. That's it.
Because this is the custom in
North Ghana,
Rose eats the hot porridge
with hands.
It is part of respecting traditions
and furthermore,
the food is tastier that way.
For the guest there is boiled
goat's meat
that is not on the table every day.
Rose's husband died
in the car accident years ago.
Her husband is buried right next
to the house
and Rose placed a big stone pile
on the grave
where she can sit and have rest
close to her husband.
Rose's income is small for a widow
and opportunity to weave baskets
is important for her,
so that she can eat Tuo Zaafi.
A lot of men who have money troubles
are involved in illegal gold mining.
They have this little gold miners
centre here.
There are lots of little gold mines
in this area.
On the surface mines where
they just dig a hole.
There is a network of buyers,
small buyers,
who buy from those who sieve
gold in the mines.
There are those who sell it on
to the next person,
who then sells it to someone for
export.
Here in a little village they use
mercury
underneath the shelter to
melt the gold.
Kwame is an attentive and helpful
young man.
He is one of the many young people
who hopes to establish himself with
gold mining.
A man has to have money
to marry a woman.
Kwame knows exactly how to get
the precious metal from the gold ore.
We go to the bush, to some place
where we go and find.
We dig it down and find the stones.
We know which stones have gold and
which ones don't have.
We bring it here
to the crushing place.
Then we take it
to the grinding machine place.
When you finish there,
then you bring it here to wash it.
Then we take the mercury and
put it in to remove the gold.
That is how we do it.
Local men mine gold in many
surrounding unregistered mines.
Even though officially it
is forbidden,
the local authority
makes exceptions
because gold mining brings in money
for many families.
Men in return are
not bothered by the restrictions
and look quite openly for ore from
old deserted mines as well
as from new underground passages
that they have dug themselves.
This is our father's land.
Nobody can come
and disturb us not to work.
This is our fore-forefather's land.
These rough men
are actually quite friendly
and allow the film crew to climb into
the gold mine.
Can you follow me?
The passages of this seemingly small
mine reach as long as 100 meters.
There are no stairs to get down
there. In order to descend
you need to be like a Spiderman with
your legs and hands spread out
leaning against the walls
of the passage.
Wooden frames are only
at the beginning of the entrance.
Am I good?
- Yes, come
In 16 meters deep the cameraman
is already out of breath.
Here you are working?
- No-no.
Not really this place.
Don't go too far!
Come, we want you to see clear!
Still going? - Yes!
- Can I get up afterwards?
Don't worry about that!
Rising back up alive
is more important
than filming rare frames
and he climbs back up.
This gold mine
does not have ventilation.
During the last few years three men
have lost their lives here,
they descended too early
after the demolition and did not
have enough oxygen in the passages.
What is there?
- Dark, there is no air.
Although gold mining in
unofficial mines is very dangerous,
locals say that
they do it day and night.
Men rest from tiredness by sleeping
on the stones,
women also go to the mines
but only to bring food and to make
sure that the men are fed.
Initial treatment of gold
takes place publicly
by the limestone square
in village centre,
where others are playing football.
Nothing is hidden
in this illegal activity.
Ore is brought to the mill in bags
being carried on the motorcycle.
The rock will be crushed
and then ground.
Remember African women's gold -
Shea tree nut had to be crushed and
ground.
Same will be done with men's
gold,
the machinery even seems to be
the same.
Ground rocks are brought outside
from a dark mill again
and washing with water next.
If Shea butter rises to top when
mixed with water
then gold sinks to the bottom -
using that gold property a cloth is
placed on the bottom of the gutter.
When rinsing the crushed and ground
gold ore with water
gold sticks on the cloth
and sand runs off it.
Then the gold dust will be washed
from the cloth
which is still mixed with mud.
A dangerous method is used
in order to bring the gold together
into a nugget.
Kwame uses mercury to get the gold.
We remember from chemistry lesson
that gold mixed with mercury forms
an amalgam - alloy.
This is the way to bring gold dust
from the mixture of minerals
together with mercury into one
nugget.
The youngsters have heard that
mercury is extremely poisonous
but they are not aware of real risks
involved with doing this work.
Liquid metal is being added with
bare hands until the fingers hold
the amalgam of mercury and gold.
After this
the most dangerous part begins -
heating the formed ball
with blowtorch.
The aim of that is to vaporise the
mercuryin order to have pure gold.
At the same time we know
that the vapours of mercury are most
dangerous.
Even breathing in
big amounts of mercury vapours
for a short time
can cause damage to lungs.
The result of the damage in
more serious cases
is permanent brain and kidney damage
or even death.
Those young men are not even using
a gas mask and risk their lives
for income.
In addition to the release of toxic
fumes and breathing them in,
the soil becomes polluted and
mercury gets into the food chain.
Local buyer is right there,
the mill belongs to him.
100 Euros will be divided between
over twenty men
that will have to pay the diggers and
also the ones treating the gold,
of whom all have put their lives
on the line.
That way each man will make
about 5 to 10 Euros.
Considering the selling price of gold
it is incredibly cheap
but many times more compared
to what the women make
from basket weaving.
But yes, gold mining is a lucky dip.
It is lucky and unlucky and income at
the same time.
You can try your luck
and dig for gold
but not go and study instead and
learn a profession.
You hope that you are lucky one day
and find a big piece of gold.
But the income is very unstable and
you cannot be sure
whether you will find anything during
six months or you might find very
small quantities. At the same time
you might hear of others who found
a big piece of gold
and ride a motorcycle in the village.
So there are different
social problems that go with it.
Kwame is on of the young men
who has not finished his education.
He needed his friend's help in order
to write his full name.
Money coming from gold is important
for all the other lines of activity
and that is why the authorities
do not bother the men.
Money that has been earned from
gold buys plenty of other services
offered by Kongo village,
for example there are
over 10 sewing workshops ...
In spite of being poor
people dress quite well.
Men have their own tailors and
women have their own.
Money also goes to hairdressers
because the hair needs to look good:
again women have women hairdressers
and men are being serviced by men.
And money also goes on transportation
the village even has one taxi.
Cars are quite old.
They are written off cars
that have probably been brought
somewhere from Europe or West.
Although they might look quite good
at the beginning
they will have dents in them soon
because of the traffic culture.
If the politicians need to go some-
where finer cars speed around here.
Sometimes small buses speed
through the holes on the road,
but the speed on these bumpy roads
should not be more than 20 km/h.
In reality these bumps on the roads
are quite dangerous, especially when
riding a motorbike. Everybody tries
to ride around the holes on the road,
and the right or left lane
get muddled.
If you are not careful there might be
a head on collision.
Time to time you can hear news of
someone getting killed in traffic
accident.
When I was here about a year ago
there was a school director's husband
who got killed that way.
He was on his bike
and a big truck basically ran over
him. Tough.
We are little bit in a hurry
so make it fast.
What is he doing there?
- I don't know what he is doing.
Little stop over to get petrol.
We got 5 l of petrol this is how they
buy it here - in small quantities.
No one
has enough money here to buy a lot.
They buy 2 spoons of sugar.
They buy a litre for the bike and for
the taxi they buy 5 litres of petrol.
Naturally the pub keeper gets a share
from the gold money,
whereas the easiest way to start a
business
in the village is to open a pub.
So the way it is here with pubs,
I am not sure what it makes then -
20 pubs per 7000 people or even more.
Quite many.
Let's peek into the pub as well.
Good morning. How are you? Fine?
An important part of the pub is a TV
in the corner. Bar counter has been
covered with net just in case that
no one will reach over the counter.
The main drinks here are beer and
soft drinks.
One of the local soft drinks here is
Malta produced by Guiness.
Local beers are Star and Club.
There are stronger drinks as well.
Beer costs 1 Euro,
people here seem responsible
but alcoholism is becoming a
serious problem.
That man goes from pub to pub and
entertains people.
That bar building is an example of
contemporary architecture.
Traditional houses are made from
clay and have grass roof.
Everyone has a dream to build
a house that is sturdier.
There are these cement blocks that
are cast and then plastered.
The house then gets a
metal or tin roof.
In a way it is unpractical because
the metal becomes very hot in the sun
and makes the rooms very hot.
At the same time it lasts longer. If
termites eat through your grass roof
in two years then metal roof will
last much longer.
And in order to bring more air into
the building
the cement blocks have holes in them
that allow the air to move.
Glass windows are not being used much
because they don't allow
the air to move much.
The schools don't have windows
but simple window and door shutters.
They are left open during the day.
Southern coast soothes the desert
heat of North Ghana.
Locals seldom traveldown to the
ocean because the trip is expensive
and takes a whole day or night.
Diana has a reason to go to the
capital city Accra
and if she goes to the sea
then going to the beach is definitely
a thing to do.
South has a paradise climate -
there is plenty of wind and sun,
water is warm.
Even though Ghana is one country,
other nations live on the coast
and houses are also built
differently.
You can see proper architecture here.
These here are holiday houses.
But in reality the houses in the
village are built the same way.
If houses are built from clay in
North Ghana
then they don't have clay here,
only a sand surface.
The easiest way to build a house is
to weave together palm tree leaves.
I suspect that those houses
will not last long,
they probably have to build a
new one every year.
Also termites eat them
and tropical storms
that come through here tangle them.
They have that kind of houses in the
neighbouring village that have fences
made from the same material. It is
very nice to sleep in those houses.
You can feel a quiet breeze blowing
through the house.
There was a small storm and very
strong rain
during the first night,
the roof leaked a bit.
I was able to move my backpack
from underneath the water coming in
at the right time.
But yes, very enjoyable.
The floors are made of sand.
Some cabins have a cement floor
but mine has a sand floor.
I think that the village houses have
a sand floor as well.
And they have this big sand bar here
before the ocean starts.
I understand that it is a protection
for them
so that when the sea levels are high
the water will not reach the village.
There are endless numbers of people
in Africa who need help.
It is another question how to help
them - give the poor people money or
find opportunities how village people
could help themselves.
By Diana's leading a choice
has been made
for developing small business
enterprise.
There is hope that through
that the basket weavers
and Shea butter producers are able
to manage independently without
help from Estonians.
Currently there are 100 women
in Kongo village
who are involved in producing Shea
butter but if there are more orders
then 200 to 300 women are ready to
come along.
Right now the first official order
has been placed,
a two ton trial shipment goes
to the US market.
Co-operative got the export
certificate and
Shea butter quality test results
were very good.
The basket weavers' co operative
started in autumn 2014 with 8 women.
Today there are
15 active craftswomen.
600 baskets that
have been sold in Estonia.
The weavers have had help from
two Estonian designers.
Mondo is helped by
Estonian volunteers,
mainly experts, teachers
and medical workers
Recently they were trying to find
someone to help explain
the health risks involved in gold
mining.
There is a plan to implement
the development and business model
in the neighbouring villages that is
used and working in Kongo village.
Locals value the work of Estonians
highly and express
their great gratitude - it wouldn't
be surprising if one day
Kongo village in Ghana was named
Estonian village.
Diana's time has come to an end in
Ghana this time.
Further work needs to be done
from Estonia
but she will go back
to Africa in few months time.
What brings me back to Africa?
I don't actually go to Africa,
I go to Kongo village. If you have
created these social ties somewhere
and started loving and respecting
these people
then you want to come back here.
I deeply care for the people
I work with and care for how they go.
I am grateful that
I have not come here once
and then left.
I have been able to observe during
four years how children grow up
and go to school
and how people develop.